BU Records: S. P. Brooks Memorial Organ Committee, Inclusive: 1931-1932, undated, Bulk: 1931 June-1932 January, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: S. P. Brooks Memorial Organ Committee
Inclusive: 1931-1932, undated, Bulk: 1931 June-1932 January, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/52
S. P. Brooks Memorial Organ Committee
2 document boxes.
The BU Records: S. P. Brooks Memorial Organ Committee consist of correspondence, financial documents, and literary productions regarding fundraising efforts to finance the purchase of an organ honoring Baylor president Samuel Palmer Brooks.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
On 1931 May 14, Samuel Palmer Brooks, president of Baylor University from 1902 to 1931, died. Only five days after Brooks’ death, the school newspaper reported that the Alumni Association was expected to make plans to establish some sort of memorial to honor President Brooks. By the end of the month, the Association decided to raise money to purchase and install a pipe organ in Waco Hall as a tribute to Brooks. They also determined to place a plaque or bust honoring Brooks in Waco Hall, and, if able to procure enough funds, to erect a chapel in Dallas at the Baylor Medical College.
In order to purchase and install a pipe organ in Waco Hall, the Alumni Association resolved to raise $40,000. Earl B. Smyth, Alumni Association president and chairman of the S. P. Brooks Memorial Organ Committee, hoped that the funds could be raised quickly so that the organ would be in place for Baylor’s 1932 commencement. Unfortunately, the Great Depression slowed fundraising efforts and it took several years to raise sufficient funds for the instrument.
Two years prior to the installation of the Brooks organ in Waco Hall, a smaller organ, called the Kimball organ, was placed in the building. Robert Markham, professor in Baylor’s organ department, designed the specifications of the Brooks organ, which was an enlargement of the Kimball organ. Dedicated on 1937 May 30, the new Brooks organ was purportedly the largest pipe organ in the Southwest at the time. During the dedicatory services, Baylor’s Board of Trustees and Mattie Sims Brooks, President Brooks' widow, presented the University with an oil painting of the former president. Also, a bronze memorial plaque was placed in the foyer of Waco Hall in commemoration of Brooks.
Scope and Content
The BU Records: S. P. Brooks Memorial Organ Committee begins in 1931 May and ends in 1936 February. Correspondence is the largest series in the collection and consists of letters regarding fundraising efforts to finance the purchase of an organ honoring Baylor president Samuel Palmer Brooks. The collection also contains financial documents and literary productions.
Arrangement
No finding aid existed for the BU Records: S. P. Brooks Memorial Organ Committee prior to the creation of this one. Most of the financial documents and literary productions in the collection were initially interspersed among the correspondence. While these financial and literary manuscripts have since been placed in their own separate series, the original order of the correspondence has been preserved.
Currently, the records of the S. P. Brooks Memorial Organ Committee are arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, III. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/52. Acquired 1973-00-00
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Samuel Palmer Brooks papers, Inclusive: 1880-1937, Bulk: 1913-1931
Related references
“Alumni Association May Erect Memorial to Honor Dr. Brooks.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1931 May 19. Accessed 2014 April 25.
“Alumni Plan to Give Brooks Memorial Organ.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1931 May 27. Accessed 2014 April 25.
"Organ, Portrait, Are Dedicated to Brooks." Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1937 May 31. Accessed 2014 April 25.
“Plans Made to Raise Memorial Organ Fund.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1931 June 4. Accessed 2014 April 25.
“Plans Made to Raise Memorial Organ Fund.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1931 June 11. Accessed 2014 April 25.
“Pres. Brooks Dies.” Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1931 May 14. Accessed 2014 April 25.
"Specifications of New Organ Stated." Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1937 May 31. Accessed 2014 April 25.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Brooks, Samuel Palmer, 1863-1931.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.; Baylor University -- Presidents.
Places
Waco Hall (Baylor University).
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Minutes (Records)
- Correspondence, 1931 May-1936 February, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series is the largest in the collection and contains letters regarding fundraising efforts to finance the purchase of an organ honoring Baylor president Samuel Palmer Brooks.
  - "Letters from Firms", 1931 August-November, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Class & Specimen Letters", 1931 September-December, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Class & Specimen Letters], 1931 September-1932 April, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Earl B. Smyth", 1931 September-1932 January (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Earl B. Smyth", 1931 May-November (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Harvey B. Carlton], 1931 September-1936 February, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Harvey B. Carlton], 1931 June-1932 January, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Harvey B. Carlton], 1931 September-1932 January, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Financial Documents, 1931 November-1932 May, undated; 2
  This series contains financial records dealing with fundraising efforts to finance the purchase of an organ honoring Baylor president Samuel Palmer Brooks.
  - "Bills & Receipts", 1931 December, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Contributions to Samuel Palmer Brooks Memorial Organ Fund", 1931 November-1932 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Literary Productions, 1931 June-1932 February, undated; 3
  This series contains literary manuscripts dealing with fundraising efforts to finance the purchase of an organ honoring Baylor president Samuel Palmer Brooks. Contents include a notebook that contains meeting minutes, letters, a list of the number of Baylor graduates by year, and a list of Baylor class secretaries. A ledger book, entitled “Brooks Memorial Organ Solicitation Lists,” contains lists of Baylor graduates by year, and the names of “Friends of Baylor and of Dr. Brooks.” The series also has a copy of the “Brooks Memorial Organ Edition of the Baylor Monthly."
  - Periodical: Brooks Memorial Organ Edition of the Baylor Monthly, 1931 October (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Two-Ring Binder, 1931 June-1932 February, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Brooks Memorial Organ Solicitation Lists", 1931 June, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)